So בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, so we pick up today on דף
קד עמוד א, Daf Kof Daled Amud Aleph, the two dots ולא
זו בלבד אמרו. V'lo Zu Bilvad Amru. So we are now finally
into some of the halakhic discussion
and we have just said that we have had some earlier discussion,
I'll talk about the הלכה למעשה Halacha L'maaseh in a minute, but
we've had some earlier discussion, we've had a ברייתא Braita that says
you can do שמע Shema in the day and the night and
in the day before and after עלות Alos and another version before
and after נץ, Netz, leaving open exactly the question when the exact
cutoff line is. And then the story of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
and saying that we rule like that the מצוה Mitzvah really goes
until the entire night until עלות, Alos, seeming to confirm that earlier
teaching that the cutoff time is עלות. Alos. Now we pick up
with that. So it's ולא זו בלבד אמרו אלא. V'lo Zu Bilvad
Amru Ela. And they didn't only say this, meaning that this is
not the only thing that can be the whole night but that
the rabbis said you're supposed to do until חצות. Chatzos. So the
גמרא Gemara says רבן גמליאל מי קאמר עד חצות דקתני ולא זו
בלבד. Rabban Gamliel Mi Ka'amar Ad Chatzos Dekatani V'lo Zu Bilvad. So
it sounds like and this is the גמרא Gemara picking up on
the ambiguity in the משנה, Mishna, it sounds like is רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel qualifying his own teaching that it's not until חצות Chatzos
or is he clarifying what the rabbis taught? So the גמרא Gemara
initially thought that he's clarifying his own teaching that he might have
of himself said חצות Chatzos and then he's saying hey guys my
kids
חצות Chatzos isn't the absolute cutoff point it's only
a safeguard. So the גמרא Gemara says but he didn't say that.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר להו רבן גמליאל לבניה, Hachi
Ka'amar Lehu Rabban Gamliel L'vanav, this is what he's saying to his
sons. אפילו רבנן דקאמרי עד חצות, Afilu Rabbanan Dekamri Ad Chatzos, I
say the whole night fine I don't even give you a cutoff
time, but even the
רבנן Rabbanan that they say until midnight מצוותה עד שיעלה עמוד השחר
Mitzvatah Ad Sheya'aleh Amud Hashachar they really agree with me that it
goes until the עמוד השחר. Amud Hashachar. והא דקאמרי עד חצות V'ha
Dekamri Ad Chatzos and why do they say חצות Chatzos כדי להרחיק
אדם מן העבירה Kedei L'harchik Adam Min Ha'aveira it's a safeguard to
save you from sin. Which raises the question is there really any
difference between him and the רבנן? Rabbanan? So it sounds like maybe
the whole difference is that the rabbis say ideally you should they
give חצות Chatzos as the first cutoff time but they would agree
that if you missed it you can go the whole night. There
are some ראשונים Rishonim תלמידי רבינו יונה Talmidei Rabbeinu Yonah that say
that no according to the רבנן Rabbanan although the motivation is rabbinic
and להרחיק אדם מן העבירה L'harchik Adam Min Ha'aveira they would actually
say that after חצות Chatzos you're no longer allowed to say. That
the רבנן Rabbanan would actually
prevent you from doing the biblical מצוה Mitzvah in order to back
up and to strengthen this line of חצות. Chatzos. Or at least
maybe that at least prevent you from doing the ברכות Brachos of
קריאת שמע Kriyas Shema but maybe even they would really hold that
line very seriously. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is saying look since this
whole thing is in order to as a safeguard they would at
least I'm saying they would agree you can do it after midnight.
And that's the way we פסקן Pasken that even if you miss
that as the גמרא Gemara says we rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel and you could do it the whole night. On the flip
side everybody says that even רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who doesn't say
חצות Chatzos as an end point would agree with the earlier ברייתא
Braita taught that you're supposed to say שמע Shema as soon as
you come home at the first opportunity so you don't get get
involved in other things and fall asleep. So everybody agrees there's an
ideal to say it you should try to say it before you
get caught up but רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says that if you
miss חצות Chatzos or anyway he says that if you don't do
it then you really have the whole night. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. הקטר
חלבים Hekter Chalavim right רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel might even not say
that חצות Chatzos is a meaningful point at all. Ideally say it
earlier but you have the whole night. Okay הקטר חלבים Hekter Chalavim
now we go on the burning of the fats is the whole
night and the eating of sacrifices is the whole night but you're
supposed to say sacrifices until חצות Chatzos eat sacrifices until חצות Chatzos
again as a safeguard. So the גמרא Gemara says ואילו באכילת פסחים
לא קתני. V'ilu B'achilas Psachim Lo Katani. But it didn't say this
by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach it said eating sacrifices but it should
have mentioned פסח Pesach as well specifically because we know there are
debates about it and it didn't mention it. So what's the איכא
Ika because we know that פסח Pesach is supposed to be until
חצות Chatzos but the question is is that biblical or is it
rabbinic? Is it rabbinic because really it's the whole night but as
we learned here you're supposed to do things until חצות Chatzos as
a safeguard or maybe it's biblical as we'll see because מכת בכורות
Makas Bechoros happened at חצות. Chatzos. So the fact that פסח Pesach
isn't mentioned here makes it sound like the reason for פסח Pesach
to do until חצות Chatzos is not rabbinic as a safeguard like
these other things but it's a real more fundamental thing it's a
biblical thing. And let's take a look. ורמינהו Urreminhu I'll ask you
on this. קריאת שמע ערבית והלל בלילי פסחים Kriyas Shema Arvis V'hallel
B'leilei Psachim קריאת שמע Kriyas Shema night like we've been saying and
saying הלל Hallel on the night of פסחים Psachim ואכילת פסח V'achilas
Pesach and the eating of the פסח Pesach מצוותן עד שיעלה עמוד
השחר Mitzvatan Ad Sheya'aleh Amud Hashachar you can do it until the
morning star comes up. We normally don't say הלל Hallel at night,
the reason we say הלל Hallel by the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
by the הגדה Haggadah is as an accompaniment to what used to
be an accompaniment to the אכילת קרבן פסח Achilas Korban Pesach could
be other reasons as well but anyway that's one of the aspects
and therefore since the פסח Pesach goes the whole night the הלל
Hallel is the whole night.
And then we said אמר
רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef so there you see that it is
in this category of things that normally could be the whole. on
night and if it's till חצות chatzos it's only a safeguard, so
why wasn't that mentioned in our משנה Mishnah in similar in that
category? אמר רב יוסף "לא קשיא". Amar Rav Yosef lo kashya.
הרב אלעזר Harav Elazar says that you could even eat it until
עמוד השחר. amud hashachar.
So תוספות Tosfos in פסחים, Pesachim, I understand, so תוספות Tosfos in
פסחים Pesachim say why don't we assume it's included in that line
of כל הנאכלים? Kol Hane'echalim? תוספות Tosfos says well it's not נאכלים
ליום ולילה אחד, ne'echalim leyom velailah echad, right? It's only eaten at
night. It's not day and night, so it's not in that. And
תוספות Tosfos says other reasons as well why the גמרא Gemara feels
that it should have mentioned קרבן פסח Korban Pesach separately and does
not think that it's included in that normal statement about normal sacrifices.
Anyway, it does not fit that description of יום ולילה, yom valailah,
it's not eaten in the day. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that
sacrifice that פסח Pesach is excluded. So the גמרא Gemara says הוה
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה או
הוה
רבי עקיבא. hava Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah o hava Rabbi Akiva. It's
a debate of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah or
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דתניא "ואכלו את הבשר בלילה הזה", Detanya: 'V'achlu
es habasar balaila hazeh', you should eat the meat of the פסח
Pesach this night. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר נאמר כאן "בלילה הזה"
ונאמר להלן "ועברתי בארץ מצרים בלילה הזה". Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah omer
ne'emar kan balaila hazeh v'ne'emar lehalan Ve'avarti be'eretz Mitzrayim balaila hazeh.
God says I'll pass through the land of Egypt on this night,
again the exact same phrase בלילה הזה. balaila hazeh. מה להלן עד
חצות, Mah lehalan ad chatzos, the same way there the event occurred
at חצות, chatzos, אף כאן עד חצות. af kan ad chatzos. So
here too at midnight and after midnight you can no longer eat
the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So that's the position of רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah and therefore according to him that's
why פסח Pesach isn't mentioned in our משנה. Mishnah. It's true it's
until חצות, chatzos, but it's not חצות chatzos as a safeguard, it's
חצות chatzos because that's the real מצוה mitzvah of קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach at חצות. chatzos. אמר לו רבי עקיבא Amar lo Rabbi Akiva
said back to him רבי עקיבא: Rabbi Akiva: ולא כבר נאמר "בחיפזון"?
v'lo kvar ne'emar b'chipazon? And you shall eat it in haste? עד
שעת חיפזון Ad sha'as chipazon means until the moment of haste, which
means until the moment when they were driven out in the next
morning, so you have the whole night to eat it. אם כן
מה תלמוד לומר "בלילה"? Im ken mah talmud lomar balaila? So why
does it say this night? יכול יאכלו כקדשים ביום, Yachol ye'achlu kekodshim
bayom, because maybe like a normal קרבן, korban, if you shechted it
in the day you start eating it the day you shechted it,
you sprinkle the blood. תלמוד לומר "בלילה". Talmud lomar balaila. No, you
only eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at night. It is a
very strange קרבן korban in that way that you offer it in
the day but you can only begin eating it at night. בלילה
הוא נאכל ולא ביום, Balaila hu ne'echal v'lo bayom, at night and
not day. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, anyway that's רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says that it's the whole
night, according to him פסח Pesach is in the category of our
משנה, Mishnah, things that could be done the whole night but the
rabbis said you should do until חצות, chatzos, but really... but רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah says you really have the
entire... I'm sorry, but he says even biblically the מצוה mitzvah really
ends at midnight. And by the
way that's the issues about what do you call it, about נו,
nu, about when people have their סדר seder whether they try to
finish the אפיקומן afikomen by חצות chatzos because the אפיקומן afikomen represents
the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, so whether you're supposed to end that
by חצות chatzos or not, how does that fit in with the
idea
of trying to be מספר ביציאת מצרים כל אותו הלילה mesaper biyetzias
Mitzrayim kol oso halailah and so on. So this has to do
partly with this question about when we think the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach itself was eaten. So now the גמרא Gemara says: בשלמא לרבי
אלעזר בן עזריה דאיכא גזירה שוה איצטריכי למיכתב "הזה". Bishlama l'Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah d'iska gezeirah shavah itztrechi lmichtav hazeh. According to רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah who's trying to specifically link it
to the מכת בכורות, makas bechoros, he had to say 'this night',
הלילה הזה, halaila hazeh, to link it to ועברתי בארץ מצרים בלילה
הזה Ve'avarti be'eretz Mitzrayim balaila hazeh to be the exact same phrase.
אלא לרבי עקיבא האי "הזה" מאי עביד ליה? Ella l'Rabbi Akiva hai
hazeh mai avid leh? Why does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva need it
to say you should eat the meat this night? Just say at
night, of course it's this night.
So the גמרא Gemara says: לאתויי לילה אחר הוא דאתא, le'atuyei laila
acher hu d'asya,
to exclude another night, meaning obviously you eat it the night of
leading into the 15th, but maybe you could eat it even the
following night like you have a good two day יום טוב. yom
tov. Why? הוה אמינא, Hava amina, I might have thought, הואיל ופסח
וקדשים קלים ושלמים קלים, ho'il u'Pesach ve'kodshim kalim v'Shelamim kodshim kalim, since
פסח Pesach is lighter sacrifices meaning eaten by ישראל Yisrael and eaten
outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the same is true
by normal שלמים. Shelamim. מה שלמים נאכלים לשני ימים ולילה אחד, Mah
Shelamim ne'echalim lishnei yamim v'laila echad, the same way שלמים Shelamim are
eaten for two days and the intervening night, you start eating it
the day that the קרבן korban is brought, אף פסח, af Pesach,
so פסח Pesach although it starts at night let it be the
mirror image, נאכל שני לילות במקום שני ימים, ne'echal shti leilos bimkom
shti yamim, let it be eaten for two nights instead of for
two days, ויאכל לשני לילות ויום אחד, v'ye'achel l'v' shti leilos v'yom
echad, let it be eaten for two nights and the intervening day.
Interesting רש"י Rashi says we don't really mean the intervening day, you
would never eat פסח Pesach in the day because it's interesting that
even in this הוה אמינא hava amina which is a strange הוה
אמינא hava amina you don't want to make it too much like
a normal קרבן, korban, it's very much associated with the event of
the גאולה Geulah so it would only be eaten at night. But
רש"י Rashi says fine but at least it wouldn't be פסול, pasul,
you'd eat it one night wait the daytime and eat it the
next night. Maybe you'd have a second night to eat it. So
קא משמע לן "בלילה
הזה". k'mashma lan balaila hazeh. No no, this night. בלילה הזה הוא
נאכל ואינו נאכל בלילה אחר. Balaila hazeh hu ne'echal v'eino ne'echal b'laila
acher. ורבי אלעזר בן
עזריה V'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah says: מ"לא תותירו
עד בוקר" נפקא, milo sosiru ad boker nafka, I get it because
the פסוק pasuk says don't leave it till the next morning, so
obviously you can't wait to finish it off the next night. רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say אם מהתם, im
me'hasam, if from there, הוה אמינא מאי בוקר? hava amina mai boker?
I would have thought what does בוקר boker mean? בוקר שני. boker
sheni. Wait till the second morning, the morning after the second night.
That doesn't prove that you only have the night.
רבי אלעזר אמר לך כל בוקר בוקר ראשון הוא. Rabbi Elazar amar
lach kol boker boker rishon hu. No, morning means the immediate next
morning. Okay, but anyway we do see that
According to רב אלעזר בן עזריה, Rav Elazar ben Azariah, that's why
it's not in our משנה, Mishnah, because it's only חצות chatzot biblically.
And according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he actually is the author
of the ברייתא Baraita that says that it is eaten the whole
night. Okay, and I should by the way point out that that
ברייתא Baraita that did say that it's eaten the whole night did
not mention that there was a rabbinic safeguard. So from the evidence
we have here, according to רב אלעזר בן עזריה Rav Elazar ben
Azariah biblically it stops at חצות, chatzot, and according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva you have the whole night without a safeguard. Either way,
it's not in our, our משנה, Mishnah, which, our משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara continues. והני תנאי כהני תנאי, ve-hanei
tannai ke-hanei tannai, these תנאים Tannaim are like the following תנאים. Tannaim.
דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: שם תזבח את הפסח
בערב, sham tizbach et ha-Pesach ba-erev, there, in the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, the place you shall slaughter the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach in
the evening time, coming up in our תורה Torah reading, כבוא השמש
מועד צאתך ממצרים, ke-vo ha-shemesh mo'ed tzeitcha mi-Mitzrayim, as the sun sets,
the time when you left Egypt. So we have a problem that
those three things are separate times. בערב ba-erev means before the sun
has set. Sun has set is a second time, and when you
left Egypt is a third time. That's the morning. So how do
you deal with these three times? So רב אלעזר אומר: Rav Elazar
omer: בערב אתה זובח, ba-erev ata zoveach, you slaughter it in the
evening time, meaning before sunset, but late afternoon. כבוא השמש אתה אוכל,
ke-vo ha-shemesh ata ochel, once the sun sets, you can begin eating
it. ומועד צאתך ממצרים אתה שורף, u-mo'ed tzeitcha mi-Mitzrayim ata soref, and
when
the day of the Exodus, meaning it's the morning time, then there's
a מצוה mitzvah to burn it. And I actually don't burn it
the morning of the 15th, because it's יום טוב. Yom Tov. You
burn it the morning of the 16th. But meaning that that is
the time of burning, at least by morning time. That's what he
says. רבי יהושע אומר: Rabbi Yehoshua omer: רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says
it sounds pretty similar. בערב אתה זובח, ba-erev ata zoveach, in the
late afternoon you slaughter it. כבוא השמש אתה אוכל, ke-vo ha-shemesh ata
ochel, when the sun sets you can eat it. ועד מתי אתה
אוכל? ve-ad matai ata ochel? How long can you eat? והולך עד
מועד צאתך ממצרים, ve-holekh ad mo'ed tzeitcha mi-Mitzrayim, and keep on going
until the time you left Egypt. You can keep on eating it
until daybreak. So it sounds like it's the exact same, except the
difference is that here he says explicitly you can eat it until
daybreak, which shows that the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is eaten the
whole night, whereas the first one says you burn it in the
day, which suggests that the time of eating might have ended earlier,
but the time of burning didn't arrive yet. So we're assuming that
that first position held like רב אלעזר בן עזריה Rav Elazar ben
Azariah and held like that the time of eating ended at חצות.
chatzot. Okay. אמר רבי אבא, amar Rabbi Abba, said רבי אבא, Rabbi
Abba, הכל מודין כשנגאלו ישראל ממצרים לא נגאלו אלא בערב, ha-kol modin
keshe-nig'alu Yisrael mi-Mitzrayim lo nig'alu ela ba-erev, everybody agrees when they were
redeemed from Egypt they were only redeemed in the evening. שנאמר, she-ne'emar,
meaning that it's appropriate to say that the גאולה ge'ulah began at
night. Nobody says we only consider the גאולה ge'ulah to be the
day. No, everybody agrees מכת בכורות makat bechorot was already considered the
גאולה. ge'ulah. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, הוציאך ה׳ אלהיך ממצרים
לילה, hotzi'acha Hashem Elokecha mi-Mitzrayim lailah, God took you out from Egypt
at night. וכשיצאו, ve-kheshe-yatze'u, the actual leaving, לא יצאו אלא ביום, lo
yatze'u ela ba-yom, it was only in the day. שנאמר ממחרת הפסח
יצאו בני ישראל ביד רמה, she-ne'emar mimachorat ha-Pesach yatze'u bnei Yisrael be-yad
ramah, the day after the פסח, Pesach, the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
they left with a יד רמה, yad ramah, with an outstretched hand.
אמר נחלקו, amar nechlaku, what did they argue? על שעת חיפזון, al
sha'at chipazon, how to describe when the תורה Torah says,
because בחיפזון, be-chipazon, you eat it in haste. When is the focus
of the moment of haste? רב אלעזר בן עזריה סבר מאי חיפזון
חיפזון דמצרים, Rav Elazar ben Azariah savar mai chipazon chipazon de-Mitzrayim, that
when it says the haste means the haste of מצרים, Mitzrayim, and
it was at midnight that מצרים Mitzrayim was already all rose up
and tried to chase בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael out. So that means
that the מצוה mitzvah goes till the time of חיפזון, chipazon, till
the time of midnight. רבי עקיבא סבר מאי חיפזון חיפזון דישראל, Rabbi
Akiva savar mai chipazon chipazon de-Yisrael, no, it means when ישראל Yisrael
was actually running out and was being chased out. דתניא נמי הכא,
de-tanya nami hacha, we taught similarly here. הוציאך ה׳ אלהיך ממצרים לילה.
hotzi'acha Hashem Elokecha mi-Mitzrayim lailah. וכי בלילה יצאו? ve-khi ba-lailah yatze'u? Did
they leave in the night? והלא לא יצאו אלא ביום? ve-halo lo
yatze'u ela ba-yom? They went out in the day. שנאמר ממחרת הפסח
יצאו בני ישראל ביד רמה. she-ne'emar mimachorat ha-Pesach yatze'u bnei Yisrael be-yad
ramah. אלא מעת שהתחילה להם גאולה מערב, ela me-eit she-hitchila lahem ge'ulah
me-erev, the redemption began at night. So what is the חידוש chiddush
of this? It's really saying the same thing we said before, you
know, do you learn it from the midnight or do you learn
it from the next day? But the חידוש chiddush seems to be,
you know, there is this question about the status we give of
the גאולה ge'ulah at night. There's a whole question of whether you
say the פרשה parsha of ציצית tzitzit at night because it mentions
זכר יציאת מצרים zecher yetzi'at Mitzrayim is why we say the third
פרשה parsha of שמע, Shema, of ציצית, tzitzit, to remember יציאת מצרים.
yetzi'at Mitzrayim. And the גמרא Gemara says, לא זכיתי שתאמר יציאת מצרים
בלילות, lo zachiti she-tei'amer yetzi'at Mitzrayim ba-leilot, a משנה Mishnah we're going
to see, that it wasn't clear that you have to remember יציאת
מצרים yetzi'at Mitzrayim at night because the real יציאה yetzi'ah happened in
the day. Of course we do פוסקין paskin you do have to
do it at night and we have the third פרשה parsha of
ציצית tzitzit at night. So that seems to be his point here.
Let's not try to question the status of nighttime as גאולה. ge'ulah.
Nighttime was גאולה ge'ulah as well. It would actually be pretty ironic
that you have the whole סדר Seder and the אכילת קרבן פסח
achilat Korban Pesach at night and we only say, but גאולה ge'ulah
was the next morning. No, גאולה ge'ulah was the night as well.
The only question is they didn't start running out. The rushing didn't
happen at night, and therefore it's a technical question of how late
do you eat the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, whether, when is the
שעת חיפזון. sha'at chipazon. But in terms of when is it considered
like the beginning of the יציאה yetziah and the beginning of the
גאולה, geulah, that everybody agrees on, which is so it ties into
that other question about the status of nighttime as the time of
גאולה. geulah. Okay. Now that we are on this discussion about מצרים
Mitzrayim we continue to have more אגדתא. Aggadeta. I should mention, obviously
it's not escape anybody's attention that there's an enormous amount of אגדתא
Aggadeta in the first פרק perek of ברכות. Brachos. This is not
just by chance, you know the ירושלמי Yerushalmi as well has an
enormous amount of אגדתא. Aggadeta. So for some reason when the, you
know there was obviously some part of the way in which this,
you know in which מסכת maseches was learned that it was always
understood that the beginning of ברכות Brachos was an opportunity to really
sort of, you know stretch out and do a lot of אגדתא.
Aggadeta. So I think that's worth reflecting on, what it means that
you know the very beginning of the very of the first מסכת
masechet of the first סדר seder in ש"ס, Shas, the גמרא Gemara
you know uses an opportunity to do a lot of אגדתא. Aggadeta.
A lot of people feel, probably myself included like okay let's get
through the אגדתא Aggadeta and get to the real discussion of the
הלכה, Halacha, but the גמרא Gemara actually interestingly really makes a point
of investing a lot of time and effort with opening ש"ס Shas
with a lot of אגדתא, Aggadeta, which might say something about how
it wants us to be sort of thinking in a framing הלכתי
halachic discussions as well, you know within those sort of larger religious
and theological terms. So with that having been said, let's continue. So
now we're talking about יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So דבר נא באזני
העם, Daber na be'oznei ha'am, God tells משה Moshe please speak to
the people and have them ask from the Egyptians all of these
vessels of gold and silver. Borrow them. So אמרי דבי רבי ינאי
Amrei devei Rabbi Yannai אין נא אלא לשון בקשה, ein na ela
lashon bakasha, נא na means please. אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה
Amar lei Hakadosh Baruch Hu le-Moshe בבקשה ממך משה bevakasha mimcha Moshe
do me a favor, לך ואמור להם לישראל lech ve-emor lahem le-Yisrael
בבקשה מכם bevakasha mikem let me say to Israel please you know
do me a favor, you משה Moshe ask a favor from Israel.
שאלו ממצרים כלי כסף וכלי זהב, Sha'alu mi-Mitzrayim klei chesef u-klei zahav,
please ask from them borrow from them objects of gold and silver.
שלא יאמר, Shelo yomar, why is this so important, it shouldn't say
אותו צדיק oso tzaddik that righteous person אברהם, Avraham, ועבדום וענו אותם
קיים בהם, va-avadum ve-inu osam kiyam bahem, oh very nice you fulfilled
the part of the of the prophecy that I will enslave them
and cause them to be oppressed. ואחרי כן יצאו ברכוש גדול, Ve-acharei
chen yetzu birchush gadol, but the end of that פסוק pasuk in
the ברית בין הבתרים bris bein habesarim that afterwards they'll go out
with great wealth, לא קיים בהם, lo kiyam bahem, that he didn't
fulfill with them. So look, you know I made them I enslaved
them and all of that I caused them to be in Egypt
I have to make sure that the end of the prophecy is
also fulfilled. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so they בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
said back to משה, Moshe, משה Moshe presumably went and said this
to them and they said back to him: ולואי שנצא בעצמנו, u-levai
she-neitzi be-atzmeinu, says don't you know look just just get us out
of here. Don't worry about the gold and silver just get us
out of here. משל לאדם שהיה חבוש בבית האסורים Mashal lo-adam she-haya
chavush be-veis ha'asurim like a person who was bound in prison והיו
אומרים לו ve-hayu omrim lo and בני אדם bnei Adam and people
would tell him: מוציאים אותך למחר, motzi'im oscha lemachar, you know tomorrow
we're going to get you out of prison מבית האסורים mi-beis ha'asurim
ונותנים לך ממון הרבה ve-nosnim lecha mammon harbeh and we'll give you
a lot of money. ואומר להם Ve-omer lahem he would say to
them: בבקשה מכם bevakasha mikem do me a favor, הוציאוני היום hotzi'uni
hayom just take me out right now ואיני מבקש כלום ve-eini mevakesh
klum I don't want any money. So don't tell me to wait
you're going to get me more money whatever just get me out
right now that is the only thing that's really of importance to
a person that is in slavery. What? It arrived. Okay. All right
so basically which is interesting because of course it does say that
they did borrow the gold and silver. But the point being that
and in a way it's like a sort of like a שבח
לישראל shevach le-Yisrael for into praise the Jewish people that that was
not of their interest they had to be encouraged to do it
all they wanted to do was to be redeemed. Okay so then
it says but it does say וישאילום va-yash'ilum they caused them they
borrowed these objects but it's a causative it's a הפעיל hif'il verb.
So they caused them to be lent to them. אמר רבי אמי
Amar Rabbi Ami מלמד שהשאילום על כרחם. melamed she-hish'ilum al korcham. So
it was against their will. So what does it mean against their
will? איכא דאמרי על כרחם דמצרים Ika de-amri al korcham de-Mitzrayim they
forced the Egyptians to lend them against the Egyptians' will. You know
they had a lot of leverage at that time.
ואיכא דאמרי על כרחם דישראל Ve-ika de-amri al korcham de-Yisrael it was
against the will of Israel. מאן דאמר על כרחם דמצרים Man de-amar
al korcham de-Mitzrayim דכתיב dichsiv ונות בית תחלק שלל ve-navas bayis techalek
shalal the one who dwelt in the house will divide the booty.
So obviously here was the slaves and the servants were now sort
of taking all of the stuff away so it's not a חידוש
chiddush that it was against the will of the Egyptians. ומאן דאמר
על כרחם דישראל U-man de-amar al korcham de-Yisrael the one who says
it was against the will of Israel why was it against their
will? I mean a minute ago we said they were sort of
saying look don't bother me with it. But the sense that it
was really enforced upon them where is that from? משום מסוי Mishum
masuy because they didn't want to have to שלעפ schlep it. Again
they were just focused on getting out they didn't want anything to
to delay them. They were willing to leave everything behind they didn't
want to have to deal with all with the burden of carrying
it. Also you know silver and gold was not top of the
priority list right now. וינצלו את מצרים, Va-yenatzlu es Mitzrayim, so it
says then it says sort of they emptied out Egypt. So what
does this word וינצלו va-yenatzlu mean? I mean it's clear from context
but what does it mean? אמר רבי אמי Amar Rabbi Ami מלמד
שעשאוה כמצודה שאין בה דגן, melamed she-asuha kimetzuda she-ein ba dagan, like
a trap that has no that has no grain in it. רש"י
Rashi says it means that they would throw grain in a pond
for the fish to come and eat it. So if they removed
all so they so it's like they removed all the... grain, and
what exactly that image is supposed to be,
but רש"י Rashi says because
what do you call it, that that you know, no, hold on,
let me just check רש"י. Rashi. Right. Right, but רש"י Rashi says,
I'm sorry, not just birds, excuse me, fish but birds, you would
throw out you would throw grain so birds would come. So you
removed all the grain, no birds are coming. So basically means they
emptied out Egypt, there was nothing there of any value, nobody else
would ever want to go to Egypt anymore, it had totally been
emptied of anything of value. ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika d'amrei, and and the
other one says, what was it? ואיכא דאמרי ריש לקיש אמר, V'ika
d'amrei Reish Lakish amar, Reish Lakish says, עשוה כמצודה שאין בה דגין.
Asuha kimsudah she'ein bah dagin. They made it not like a מצודה,
metzudah, like a trap that has no that has no grain,
but they made it like a pond that has no fish. So
all of the fish, I guess the רש"י Rashi says, you know,
at the top, at the bottom of the pond there is no
fish. Same type of an idea though, that there is nothing there
of any value that is left. Although, you know, the slightly different
image. The trap with no grain means nobody has any reason to
go there because there's nothing of value for anybody to come and
take anything else from it. Grain is a thing being taken. Here
it's like everything of value was already removed. Slightly different image. Anyway,
moving on, it says like this, אהיה אשר אהיה. Ehyeh asher ehyeh.
Now we're just dealing a little more of אגדתא, Agadata, a little
a little no longer with the storyline of emptying out Egypt, but
okay. Moshe's got to, to Moshe, I will be who I will
be, when he asks him for the name. So what does this
mean? אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, Amar lei HaKadosh Baruch Hu
l'Moshe, לך אמור להם לישראל, Leich emor lahem l'Yisrael, אני הייתי עמכם
בשעבוד זה ואני אהיה עמכם בשעבוד מלכויות. Ani hayiti imachem b'shibud zeh
v'ani eheyeh imachem b'shibud malchuyot. Says, "I will be that I will
be, I was with you in the past, I was with you
in this exile, I'll be with you in future exiles of the
other
kingdoms." אמר לפניו, Amar lifanav, so Moshe said to God, ריבונו של
עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, master of the universe, דייה לצרה בשעתה, Dayah
l'tzarah b'sha'atah, great line. You know, the the affliction is enough at
its time. Let's not- don't bother me with other afflictions, you know,
this is bad enough for for what it is right now. So
דייה לצרה בשעתה. Dayah l'tzarah b'sha'atah. אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar
lei HaKadosh Baruch Hu, לך אמור להם, Leich emor lahem, go say
to them, אהיה שלחני אליכם. Ehyeh shelachani aleichem. Fine. I can see
the point. אהיה, Ehyeh, I'm with you in this צרה, tzarah, we
don't need to mention other צרות tzarot right now. Okay. So it's
a good- also it's a good phrase, you know, you're dealing with
a trouble and somebody says, "Yeah, but what about if this happens,
what about if this happens?" and you're דייה לצרה בשעתה. Dayah l'tzarah
b'sha'atah. Let's just worry about this problem right now, we'll worry about
other things later. So that's what Moshe said to God and God
conceded the point.
ענני ה' ענני. Aneini Hashem aneini. Now for some reason because we're
having it seems to be a little bit of a like a
double language אהיה אשר אהיה Ehyeh asher Ehyeh
and a dialogue with Moshe with God, we pack- you know, it
we bring in this other פסוק pasuk by אליהו Eliyahu and God.
So אליהו Eliyahu says to God, "Answer me God, answer me." We
had quoted this before when he was trying to prove that God
was the true God against the prophets of the בעל. Ba'al. אמר
רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, למה אמר אליהו ענני שתי פעמים? Lama
amar Eliyahu aneini shtei pe'amim? Why did אליהו Eliyahu say it twice?
מלמד שאמר אליהו לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Melamed she'amar Eliyahu lifnei HaKadosh
Baruch Hu, אליהו Eliyahu says to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel
Olam, master of the universe, ענני שתרד אש מן השמים, Aneini sheteired
eish min hashamayim, answer me that that a fire should come from
heaven, ותאכל כל אשר על המזבח, v'tochal kol asher al hamizbeiach, and
answer everything on the altar, וענני שתסיח דעתם כדי שלא יאמרו מעשה
כשפים הם, va'aneini shetasiach da'atam kedei shelo yomru ma'aseh keshafim heim,
that you should distract them that they should not be able to
say that, "Oh, maybe the whole thing is just witchcraft." It's interesting
like distract them because, you know, there'd be no answer. How do
you prove a negative? How do you prove it's not witchcraft? So
the only- so what he was asking for wasn't that there somehow
evidence that it shouldn't be witchcraft. Somebody who wants to find a
reason to doubt or to cast, you know, or to cast aspersions
will do it, but but make them so overwhelmed. Okay, make them
so overwhelmed by the experience, you know, that they don't even think
to suggest that. שנאמר ואתה הסבות את לבם אחורנית, Shene'emar v'atah hasibota
et libam achoranit, you have caused their hearts to turn, you know,
to turn backwards, so, you know, that they are fa- it's easy
for them to find excuses, so the- so- please help me that
that doesn't happen this time. Okay. So that was an interesting end
of the אליהו Eliyahu bit, but anyway, we had the whole discussion
about יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim because we were mentioning חצות Chatzot or
the daybreak as the time of גאולה Geulah for the question of
whether קרבן פסח Korban Pesach מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin is eaten the
whole night or מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin is only eaten until חצות
Chatzot and not as a safeguard but because that is the time
of גאולה. Geulah. Okay, so with that we ended discussion about how
long in is the night שמע Shema and now was this משנה
mishnah we talk about הלכה halacha in a little bit, with this
משנה mishnah we turn to the question of when is the day
שמע. Shema. So let's take a look. מאימתי קורין את שמע בשחרית?
Me'imatai korin et shema b'shacharit? Till when do you read שמע Shema
in the morning? משיכיר בין תכלת ללבן. Mishiakir bein techelet l'lavan. It
doesn't say when you start interestingly, although מאימתי Me'imatai would certainly suggest
at least we're dealing with the start point. I'm sorry, it doesn't
say- excuse me, I take that back about when you end. It
does say. I'm sorry, forget everything, forget it, strike that. משיכיר בין
תכלת ללבן. Mishiakir bein techelet l'lavan. From the- it's from the time
you can distinguish between תכלת, techelet, between like the light blue of
ציצית tzitzit and the white. רבי אליעזר אומר בין תכלת לכרתי, Rabbi
Eliezer omer bein techelet l'karti, from the blue to כרתי karti which
is like a green color. עד, Ad, so that's the starting point,
right? It does say both the starting and the ending. עד, Ad,
so that's when it starts, from this time of discernment which is
presumably sometime after
עלות השחר. alot hashachar. sometime after the morning star and before sunrise.
עד הנץ החמה Ad hanetz hachama until the until the the rising
of the sun, on the shining of the sun. By the way
people say נץ החמה, netz hachama,
it's a mistake. הנץ החמה, heneitz hachama, the ה hei is not
a ה hei of the, it's part of the word here of
the shining, הנץ. heneitz. So anyway, the shining of the sun. רבי
יהושע אומר עד שלש שעות. Rabbi Yehoshua omer ad shalosh shaot. No,
you don't have the end cut as rising of sun, it's three
hours into the day שכן דרך מלכים לעמוד בשלש שעות. shekein derech
melachim la'amod beshalosh shaot. Kings get up three hours into the day.
הקורא מכאן ואילך, Hakorei mikan ve'eilach, if you read שמע shma after
the end point, whether it's הנץ החמה heneitz hachama or שלש שעות,
shalosh shaot, לא הפסיד כאדם הקורא בתורה. lo hifsid k'adam hakorei batorah.
So it's at least like you're reading פסוקים pesukim in the תורה,
Torah, you're not doing the מצוה mitzvah of שמע, shma, but at
least you're reading פסוקים pesukim in the תורה. Torah. The question is
going to be, can you still do it with the ברכות brachot
of קריאת שמע krias shma which the גמרא Gemara will discuss. But
here we find a fascinating thing that it's possible that the time
of קריאת שמע krias shma ends at sunrise. Whoever thought such a
thing? But to some degree it does parallel the first opinion in
the משנה, mishna, which is that the night שמע shma ends three
hours or four hours into the night, that it's not
while it's the period of rising, the period of sleeping. So the
period of rising, you know, for people that work the land and
for farmers or whatever, if you're not a king or בני מלכים,
bnei melachim, you get up by sunrise. You know what's the phrase,
right? What is it, a man works from sun to sun, and
the end of it is but a woman's work is never done.
But anyway, so that's why, you know, in a time without electricity
and you're working the land, it's from sunrise to sunset. So you
start going to bed pretty soon after sunset and you get up
by sunrise. So that's the first opinion, that the period of people
getting up is a very small period. The other opinion really doesn't
disagree in principle, it just says that people get up a few
more hours into the day, they get up until three o'clock until
three hours into the day. But it is interesting that according to
one opinion, the window of morning שמע shma is very small. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
מאי בין תכלת ללבן? Mai bein techeilet lelavan? What does it mean
to distinguish between the blue and the white? אילימא בין גבבא דעמרא
חיורא לגבבא דעמרא תכלתא? Eeleima bein gvava de'amra chivara legvava de'amra tichleta?
If it's between like a, you
know,
a גבבא gvava like a, what is it called, a mass, some
type of you know of a pile
of white wool and a pile of blue wool.
הבליילי נמי מידעי ידעי? Habeleila nami miv'ei yaidia? You can see that
even at night you know you can see. I mean you won't
see that it's clearly blue but you can see a difference between
white and blue.
Where were we? אלא בין תכלת שבו ללבן שבו. Ela bein techeilet
shebo lelavan shebo. Between the blue of the ציצית tzitzit and the
white of the ציצית. tzitzit. Why is that harder to discern? Because
if the, you know, the כריכות krichot when you wrap them, the
areas between the knots, so if they alternate between blue and white
at that and there, so they're right juxtaposed to one another, right
next to one another. You know, so if it's not good light,
it'll all blur, it'll all look pretty much the same, it'll all
look colored. So it has to be good light so you see
that right next to a blue string is also a white string.
So that requires that there to be more light outside and it
be a little bit into the day.
תניא Tanya רבי מאיר אומר. Rabi Meir omer. רבי מאיר Rabi Meir
says משיכיר בין זאב לכלב. mishi'yakir bein ze'ev lekelev. You see the
difference between a wolf and a dog. You know they had wild
dogs, they weren't so different from wolves at those times. רבי עקיבא
אומר Rabi Akiva omer בין חמור לערוד. bein chamor le'arod. Between a
domesticated donkey and a wild donkey. אחרים אומרים, Achereim omrim, others say
משיכיר את חברו רחוק ארבע אמות ויכירנו. mishi'yireh et chaveiro rachok arba
amot veyakirenu. You see your friend ארבע אמות arba amot away, six
feet away and you recognize him. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi says, what are
you talking about? If it's a good friend, you see him from
much further. If it's somebody you don't know so well, you barely
recognize him even when he's right in front of you. So it
says, alright somebody you know in passing. So you know him okay
but not super well. Anyway, then it continues. אמר רב הונא הלכה
כאחרים. Amar Rav Huna halacha k'achereim. We rule like the אחרים. achereim.
All of these you know this all of this is generally called
in הלכה halacha משיכיר. mishi'yakir. And
different times are given משיכיר mishi'yakir but normally I should say that
the period of עלות alot is assumed to be seventy-two minutes before
sunrise and the period of משיכיר mishi'yakir is normally assumed to be
about forty-five minutes
before sunrise. So for example, I looked up today, while here I
am in Atlanta, sunrise is 6:52 according to my little
זמנים zmanim calendar and there are two versions of משיכיר. mishi'yakir. The
forty-five minute version puts it at 6:07 and the some say eleven
degrees before you know before the sun rises, so that's 5:58. So
anyway, it's somewhere between forty-five minutes to an hour before sunrise based
on different opinions and עלות alot is 5:40, seventy-two minutes before sunrise.
So those are some very critical halachic times. עלות alot is the
basic beginning of the halachic day. There's a question about קריאת שמע
krias shma we'll get to, you know, הנץ החמה. heneitz hachama. is
when מצוות mitzvos generally, day מצוות mitzvos generally can be done בדיעבד
b'di'eved as early as עלות, Alot, but they're supposed to be done
only from הנץ החמה, Hanetz Hachama, and הנץ החמה Hanetz Hachama is
important for שמע, Shema, שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, and ותיקין Vatikin as
we've seen, and משיכיר Misheyakir is important for תפילין. Tefillin. And it's
also
presumably important for ציצית Tzitzis as we're seeing here, for at least
the משנה Mishnah's idea of the beginning of the time of קריאת
שמע, Krias Shema, this period of משיכיר. Misheyakir. So he has that
according to the משנה, Mishnah, the first opinion gives you an hour
about or forty-five minutes from משיכיר Misheyakir until sunrise. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, הלכה
כאחרים. Halacha k'Acherim. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לתפילין כאחרים, L'tefillin k'Acherim, when
it comes to תפילין Tefillin it's like אחרים, Acherim, meaning we do
משיכיר Misheyakir like I just said, the time people know that if
you daven early in the winter or whatever, you sometimes wait to
put on the טלית ותפילין tallis v'tefillin because to משיכיר. Misheyakir. You
can start davening earlier from עלות, Alot, but טלית ותפילין tallis v'tefillin
is משיכיר, Misheyakir, so that's what אביי Abaye is saying. לקריאת שמע
כותיקין, L'krias Shema k'Vatikin, קריאת שמע Krias Shema goes like
ותיקין, Vatikin, דאמר רבי יוחנן, D'amar Rabi Yochanan, ותיקין היו גומרים אותה
עם הנץ החמה. Vatikin hayu gomrim osah im hanetz hachama. The ותיקין,
Vatikin, which is like ותיקין, Vatikin, first of all what that means,
if somehow it's a phrase talking people that were very scrupulous in
מצוות mitzvos or the ancient ones, anyway, people that were very scrupulous
in this practice would finish the שמע Shema with the rising of
the sun, with הנץ החמה. Hanetz Hachama. So they would not do
it early, they would try to situate it right at הנץ. Hanetz.
Why is that significant? Let's take a look. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya
nami hachi, we taught similarly, ותיקין היו גומרים אותה עם הנץ החמה.
Vatikin hayu gomrim osah im hanetz hachama. The ותיקין Vatikin used to
finish the שמע Shema with the rising of the sun, כדי שיסמוך
גאולה לתפילה, k'dei sheyisomoch geulah l'tefillah, so that they should juxtapose redemption
to prayer. Redemption is גאל ישראל Ga'al Yisrael at the end of
שמע, Shema, שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, ונמצא מתפלל ביום, v'nimtza mispalel bayom,
and pray during the day. So meaning it starts like this. You
want your תפילה tefillah to be at the day, meaning שמע Shema
is supposed to be when you're rising up, not yet when it's
fully day. So שמע, Shema, you know, it starts from משיכיר, Misheyakir,
goes until הנץ החמה, Hanetz Hachama, whatever it is, that's when you're
rising up. But תפילה tefillah for some reason, the idea is is
that you want that to very much be full day, you want
it to be after הנץ החמה. Hanetz Hachama. So and as such,
if you're going to have תפילה, tefillah, so how do you get
these two to satisfy these two criteria? How do you get שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei in daytime and שמע Shema before sunrise? According to
the first opinion in the משנה, Mishnah, the period of שמע Shema
ends before sunrise. So the only way to do it is you
end שמע Shema exactly right before, during or right before sunrise, the
exact last minute of saying שמע, Shema, and then you go right
into שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei because you have to go straight מסמיכת
גאולה לתפילה, m'semichas geulah l'tefillah, and you get שמע Shema within its
right time and שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei ביום bayom after sunrise, and
that's how the period of ותיקין, Vatikin, and that's what the ותיקין
Vatikin used to be to fulfill both שמע Shema and שמונה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esrei. Okay, so we'll take a let's look a little bit
more as this develops. אמר רבי זירא מאי קרא, Amar Rabi Zeira
mai kra, what's the פסוק? pasuk? יראוך עם שמש ולפני ירח דור
דורים. Yira'ucha im shemesh v'lifnei yarei'ach dor dorim.
They will fear you with the sun and and before the moon
for all generations, which is understood to be the fear of you
comes with the sun. So רש''י Rashi says the fear of you
means קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, which is קבלת עול מלכות שמים, Kabbalas
Ol Malchus Shamayim, and that's with the sun, that's right at the
moment of sunrise, which is interesting because normally the emphasis of ותיקין
Vatikin emphasizes not the שמע Shema aspect but the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei aspect, that the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei comes during during sunrise
and there's a power to that as well, not just as I
said, that if you want to get שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei in
the day and שמע Shema ends by sunrise, the only way to
do it is exactly at that moment, but also that there's like
a power of davening with the rising sun, like that sense of
day breaking and experiencing, you know, God and the power and the
majesty of God and the creation and so on, and doing it
as the sun is rising, there's a certain power in that. So
it's possible to read this פסוק pasuk not like רש''י Rashi that
the fear refers to שמע Shema with the sun but refers to
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei with the sun. But anyway, so that's another
aspect of ותיקין, Vatikin, not just the way to get them both
in their right time and get them juxtaposed, but the power of
saying either the שמע Shema according to רש''י Rashi or the שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei at that moment of sunrise, there's a very particular
power to that. And I should mention by the way that the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that the reason we have davening in the morning,
afternoon, and evening is not because of the or not only in
addition to the reason of the קרבנות korbanos as we're going to
see later, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi also says it's because of the sun
rising and, you know, the sun in the in the middle of
the day and the sun setting and responding to what's going on
in nature and sort of experiencing God through those natural experiences, through
those natural phenomena. So that's I think another aspect of what this
ותיקין Vatikin is. So here we have this idea of ותיקין Vatikin
*vatikin* and there are people that are very מקפיד *makpid* to do
ותיקין *vatikin* which means the time they דאוון *daven* changes every day
and actually the הלכה Halacha *halacha* is that for people that are
מקפיד *makpid* to do ותיקין *vatikin*, if you do it regularly then
it's even of more importance than תפילה tefillah בציבור *tefilla b'tzibbur*. So
this really becomes a certain type of a very sort of valued
experience
type of way of דאוונינג *davening* is right before saying שמע Shema
*Shema* and then going right into שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei. *Shemoneh Esrei*
at sunrise. I will just say a point that I did say
before though that sometimes what can be funny about ותיקין מניינים *vatikin
minyanim* is there they are, they have it down from their calendar
that sunrise is 6:13 and 23 and 23.23
parts of a second and everybody's like checking their watch so that
they end שמע Shema *Shema* exactly at the moment they say גאל
ישראל *ga'al Yisrael* they go into שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei*,
but the whole experience then becomes one of looking at the watch,
not one of sort of responding to the rising sun and being
in sort of that type of connection with nature. So it's a
little funny sometimes how that experience takes place. But that is the
experience of ותיקין *vatikin* and that's what אביי Abaye *Abbaye* is saying.
He's saying don't do the משיכיר Misheyakir. *misheyakir*, that's fine for תפילין
*tefillin*, but when it comes to
שמע Shema *Shema*, here's the best way to be saying שמע Shema
*Shema* right after or before the rising sun. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on. העיד רבי אמי בר אבא משום קהלא
קדישא דבירושלים *Heidid Rabbi Ami bar Abba mishum deila d'ka de'it b'Yerushalayim*,
כל הסומך גאולה geulah לתפילה *kol hasomech geulah l'tefillah*, so interesting, in
the name of the holy congregation of Jerusalem, which sounds again like
it was like the community that did this type of a special
practice, whoever juxtaposes redemption with שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei*, אינו
ניזוק כל היום כולו *eino nizak kol hayom kulo*, is not damaged
for the entire day. Now the point is like תוספות tosafos *Tosafot*
says, what's this big thing? We all do שמע Shema, *Shema* and
שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei*. But it means in this way,
so that it's right at the moment of sunrise so that and
that's very hard to time that שמע Shema *Shema* right into שמונה
עשרה Shmonah Esrei, *Shemoneh Esrei*, שמע Shema *Shema* right before sunrise, שמונה
עשרה Shmonah Esrei. *Shemoneh Esrei* right at sunrise. And if you do
that, you'll be protected the whole day. אמר רב זירא *Amar Rav
Zeira*: איני *Ini?* Is that really true? ואנא סמכי *Va'ana samchi*, I
did that, ואיצקי *v'itziki*, and I was damaged, I got hurt on
one day. אמרי ליה במאי איצקת *Amlei bemai itzakas?* How do you
feel you were hurt? דאמטיית אסא לבי מלכא *D'amtiyis asa l'vei malka*,
they demanded that you bring some myrtle, הדס *hadas*, to the king's
house, to the castle. התם נמי דבעי לך למייהב אגרא למחזי אפי
מלכא *Hatam nami bevayei lach lemeiv agra l'mechezei apey malka*, that actually
wasn't a damage, that was a reward. Under other circumstances, you would
have had to have paid a fee in order to have appeared
before the king. That was something wonderful. Look, you thought you had
a schlep and do this, but you got to see the king.
דאמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, לעולם ישתדל אדם לרוץ לקראת מלכי ישראל
*D'amar Rabbi Yochanan: Le'olam yishtadel adam larutz likrat malchei Yisrael*, a person
should always run to see the Jewish kings, ולא לקראת מלכי ישראל
בלבד *v'lo likrat malchei Yisrael bilvad*, not just Jewish kings, אלא אפילו
לקראת מלכי עובדי כוכבים ומזלות *ella afilu likrat malchei akum*, even non-Jewish
kings, שאם יזכה יבחין בין מלכי ישראל למלכי עובדי כוכבים ומזלות *she'im
yizkeh yavchin bein malchei Yisrael l'malchei akum*, because if you merit to
actually see kings of ישראל *Israel* in the time of משיח Mashiach,
*Mashiach*, I mean, nowadays we have a president or prime minister, anyway,
if you merit then you'll appreciate, you'll have a sense of royalty
if you see them, and that sense of royalty will be important
because then you can also see the difference which probably is echoing
back some of the earlier גמרות *Gemaras* about דוד David. *David* contrasting
what it meant for him to be a king, a king of
ישראל *Israel*
as opposed to the non-Jewish kings, with their gold crowns and all
of their material honor as opposed to sort of what his role
was as a Jewish king. So maybe that possibly is echoing that
back. Anyway, so that's it, the value of ותיקין *vatikin*. אמר ליה
amar leh, רבי אילא לעולא *Amlei Rabbi Illa l'Ulla*: רבי אילא *Rabbi
Illa* said to עולא *Ulla*, כי עיילת להתם *ki ayils l'hisam*, when
you go there to ישראל *Israel*, שאל בשלומו דרבי ברונא אחי *sha'al
b'shlama d'Rabbi Bruna achai*, ask after the well-being of רבי ברונא *Rabbi
Bruna* my brother במעמד כל החבורה *v'ma'amad kol hachaburah* where in the
entire community is around, ask about his welfare, which is apparently a
way of showing respect that everybody's there and you're saying and how
is רבי אחי *Rabbi Achai* and so on, and this is a
request from the name of רבי אילא *Rabbi Illa*. So why? דאדם
גדול הוא *D'adam gadol hu*, he's a great person, ושמח במצוות *v'sameach
b'mitzvot*, he rejoices over the opportunity to do מצוות *mitzvot*. זימנא חדא
סמך גאולה geulah, לתפילה *Zimna chada samach geulah l'tefillah*, one day he
managed to juxtapose גאולה geulah *geulah* redemption to שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei
*Shemoneh Esrei*, ולא פסיק חוכא מפומיה כל היום כולו *v'lo pasik chucha
mipumei kol hayoma*, and the smile didn't leave his face the entire
day. So he so much rejoices over the opportunity to do מצוות
*mitzvot* in the right way. And again, presumably this means to דאוון
*daven* ותיקין *vatikin*. היכי מצי סמך *Heichi mati samach?* Now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, is it really possible that we really fully juxtapose
גאולה geulah, *geulah* to תפילה tefilla. *tefillah*? והאמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Veha'amar Rabbi Yochanan*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says, בתחילה הוא אומר *b'tchila
hu omer*, originally at the beginning you say, ה' שפתי תפתח hashem
sefasai tiftach? *Hashem sefatai tiftach*, God open up my lips, that's what
you say at the beginning of שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei. *Shemoneh Esrei*,
that's not part of the שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei* per
se, we get it from the teaching of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*,
ולבסוף הוא אומר *u'v'sof omer*, at the end you say יהיו לרצון
אמרי פי yihyu leratzon imrei phi, *Yihyu l'ratzon imrei fi*, let the
words of my mouth be for
find favor. So the problem is you say ה' שפתי hashem sefasai
תפתח *Hashem sefatai tiftach*, that's therefore there's not something
interrupting. אמר רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Elazar*: תהא דתפילה של ערבית arvis
*Tehei d'tefilla shel arvit* so you say that. שחרית Shacharis, where it's
really about juxtaposing them as we taught, you know, this whole thing
about that the עיקר גאולה ikkar geulah is in the day, and
there it's very clear that שמע Shema, leads into שמונה עשרה. Shmonah
Esrei. There don't say
השם שפתי תפתח. Hashem Sifasai Tiftach. So רבי יוחנן, איזהו בן עולם
הבא הוא, eizu ben olam haba hu, who is a person who
merits the world to come, הסומך גאולה של ערבית לתפילה של ערבית,
hasomech geulah shel arvis letfillah shel arvis,
by having the גאולה geulah of night go into the שמונה עשרה
shmoneh esrei, of night. Remember there was an opinion before that said
first you do שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei. then שמע Shema. because that
makes שמע Shema more בשכבך beshochbecha when you go to sleep. But
here we favor more the classic sort of fixed liturgy and it's
שמע Shema leads into שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei even at night. And
there's a concept of being סומך גאולה לתפילה somech geulah letfillah and
we actually do very much night is as well a period of
גאולה, geulah. so it also is important, not as important as day
as we discussed earlier, but it's still important and there still is
that concept. אלא רבי אלעזר תהא בתפילת המנחה פי, Ella Rabbi Elazar
tei betfillas hamincha pi, so only say השם שפתי תפתח Hashem Sifasai
Tiftach at מנחה, Mincha, don't say it at שחרית, don't say it
at מעריב. Maariv. So רב אשי אמר אפילו תימא כולה. Rav Ashi
amar afilu teima kula. No, say it at all the times like
we do. דכיון דקבוע רבנן בתפילה, de-keivan de-kavu'a rabbanan bitfillah, since the
Rabbis established it as part of the prayer, כתפילה אריכתא דמיא, ketfillah
arichta damya, it's like an extended prayer. אי לאו כהא הכי, i
lo ke-ha hachi, if you don't say that, ערבית היכי מצי סמיך,
heich masi samach, how can we juxtapose גאולה geulah and תפילה tefilla.
at night? ובעי למימר ve-aba leimemar השכיבנו, hashkivenu, you say even another
ברכה bracha that's not about the גאולה, geulah. you say השכיבנו. hashkivenu.
אלא כיון דתקינו רבנן השכיבנו, ella keivan detakinu rabbanan hashkivenu, once they
established it as part of the דאווענען, davening, כגאולה אריכתא דמיא, kigeulah
arichta damya, it's like an extended saying of the גאולה even though
it's not really the theme of the גאולה. הכא נמי, hacha nami,
here too, כיון דקבוע רבנן בתפילה, keivan dekabu'a rabbanan bitfillah, since they
established it as part of the שמונה עשרה, shmoneh esrei כתפילה אריכתא
דמיא, ketfillah arichta damya, it's like a long part of שמונה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esrei Now obviously there's a good proof because it's much easier
to say השם שפתי תפתח Hashem Sifasai Tiftach is part of the
שמונה עשרה than it is to say that השכיבנו hashkivenu is part
of גאולה which has nothing to do with the theme of גאולה.
So it is a pretty good קל וחומר. kal vachomer. I should
also mention that we saw this earlier in the גמרא gemara when
the גמרא gemara introduced השכיבנו hashkivenu and it made the proof the
exact opposite way. How could you say השכיבנו? hashkivenu? What about סומך
גאולה לתפילה? somech geulah letfillah? And it says, oh, but look, the
same way we say השם שפתי תפתח Hashem Sifasai Tiftach and we
say once it's part of the liturgy it's not a problem, we'll
say the same thing, it's like תפילה אריכתא, tefillah arichta, we'll say
השכיבנו, hashkivenu, that's גאולה אריכתא. geulah arichta. So it's pretty funny when
you're dealing with case A you prove it from case B, and
when you're dealing with case B you prove it from case A.
So obviously it's sort of saying they're both problems and they're both
answered the same way that that becomes part of the liturgy and
it's not considered therefore an interruption. I should also mention now that
we are talking about adding the השם שפתי תפתח Hashem Sifasai Tiftach
that it is very interesting, you know, that very much "God open
up my lips" and then the ending יהיו לרצון אמרי פי, yihyu
leratzon imrei phi, you know, very much sort of, well, it does
two things I would say to the שמונה עשרה. One thing it
does is it personalizes it in the sense that it's first person
singular and not first person plural, like the entire שמונה עשרה is
first person plural, אלהינו ואלהי אבותינו, Elokeinu v'elokei avoseinu, which is obviously
very important and powerful about being part of the ציבור tzibbur and
being מתפלל mispallel at the time of the ציבור tzibbur with a
ציבור tzibbur in the language that you see yourself not as an
individual but it does take away a little bit of that sort
of very personal experience of דאווענען. davening. So the השם שפתי תפתח
ופי, Hashem Sifasai Tiftach u-phi, יהיו לרצון אמרי פי, yehiyu leratzon imrei
fi, my mouth, my mouth, singular, very much personalizes, frames the דאווענען
davening also in a much more personal way. The other thing that
it does, you know, is in the larger discussion which we'll get
to in a week or so, or two weeks, about תפילה כנגד
קרבנות, tefillah keneged korbanos, how much is this sort of something that
stands in for קרבנות korbanos and how much is this something that
is really just a direct way to approach God and not some
substitute for קרבנות. korbanos. The interesting thing is if you look at
the פסוק pasuk of השם שפתי תפתח Hashem Sifasai Tiftach in תהלים,
Tehillim, it's followed with כי לא תחפוץ עולה וזבח. ki lo sachpotz
olah va-zevach. That after it says God accept the words of my
mouth it says because you do not desire a burnt offering or
a sacrifice. That actually that פסוק, pasuk, the end of that פסוק
pasuk actually emphasizes that verbal prayer is preferred over sacrifices. So that's
actually quite interesting that that is a פסוק pasuk that is chosen
to open up the שמונה עשרה. So that is the statement of
רבי יוחנן and here being brought to to talk about the issue
about being סומך גאולה לתפילה. somech geulah letfillah. All right, so now
we sort of continue this. Is everybody still there on the line?
Hello? Yeah. Okay, fine. All right, so now we continue. Yeah. Okay.
So now it says like this: מכדי האי יהיו לרצון אמרי פי,
Michti hai yihyu leratzon imrei phi, this פסוק, pasuk, "let the words
of my mouth be for desire," משמע לבסוף ומשמע מעיקרא, mashma d'basof
umashma de-kara, it means the words that I said in the past
that they be for desire or means the words that I am
about to say find desire in your eyes. דבעינא למימר, de-ba'ina leimeimar,
that I want that I'm about to say. מאי טעמא תקינו רבנן
mai ta'ama takinu rabbanan לאחר י"ח ברכות, l'achar yod ches brachos, לימא
מעיקרא? leimar m'ikara? Why not use this to open up the שמונה
עשרה, יהיו לרצון yehiyu leratzon? אמרי פי, why open with ה' שפתי
hashem sefasai, תפתח? אמר רב יהודה, amar rav yehuda, אקשי, akshei, you
know, there's something else beautiful besides the context I just mentioned about
ה' שפתי in the context of God not desiring sacrifices, more desiring
our prayers. Also, there's something very beautiful about the ה' שפתי, which
is not just that the words find favor, but also sort of
reflects the idea of a person struggling to find the right words
and sort of a certain sense of almost like trepidation and anxiety
approaching God, help me open up my mouth. So there's obviously something,
I think, clearly more powerful about that as an opener than just
let my words find favor. But that's the גמרא'ס gemara's question, why
not open with יהיו לרצון? yehiyu leratzon So it could also mean
that I'm about to say. So it says, אמר רבי יהודה בריה
דרבי שמעון בן פזי, amar rabbi yehuda breih de-rabbi shimon ben pazi,
הואיל ואמרו דוד לאחר י"ח פרשיות, ho'il v'amru david l'achar yod ches
parshiyos, since David only said it after eighteen parshiyos, it comes at
the end of תהילים י"ט. tehillim yod tes. Therefore, לפיכך תיקנו רבנן
לאחר י"ח ברכות, lefichach tiknu rabanan l'achar yod ches brachos, they said
it after the eighteen ברכות brachos of the שמונה עשרה. The problem
is that David said it not at the end of eighteen, it's
at the end of פרק י"ט, perek yod tes, which is what
the גמרא gemara says. הני י"ח י"ט הויין. hani yod ches yod
tes havyan. These are 18, they're 19? אשרי האיש ולמה רגשו גוים
חדא פרשה היא. ashrei ha-ish u-lama ragshu goyim chada parsha hi. No,
actually, it says that the first two פרקים prakim of תהילים, tehillim,
it's quite interesting, you know, that these are, there's not a clear
end to פרק א'... perek aleph... what? Hello? You're breaking up. I
can't do anything about that. You are breaking up. I know, I
can't do anything about that. Is that better? Hello? A little. All
right, sorry. Anyway, the end, the first פרק perek of תהילים tehillim
is very short and it doesn't end with a clear ending. It
just says כי יודע ה' דרך צדיקים ודרך רשעים תאבד. ki yode'a
hashem derech tzaddikim v'derech resha'im toved. למה רגשו גוים ולאומים יהגו ריק
lama ragshu goyim u-le'umim yehgu rik is the next פרק perek of
תהילים, tehillim, but there's no ending, clear ending, right? Everything else opens
אשרי, ashrei, למנצח. lamnatze'ach. פרק ב' perek beis of תהילים, tehillim, if
you ever looked at it, does not have a clear opening word
like every other פרק perek of תהילים tehillim does. הללויה, hallelujah, אשרי,
ashrei, none of that. So it says really פרק א' perek aleph
and פרק ב' perek beis are one פרק perek of תהילים, tehillim,
which is interesting, which is why were they ever divided, but it
says in truth they are one פרק. perek. So the גמרא gemara
says where are we? ואמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן.
v'amar rabbi shmuel bar nachmani amar rabbi yochanan. Here's another proof that
they're really one פרק, perek, because we say ק"ג פרשיות, kuf gimmel
parshiyos, אמר דוד, amar david, David said, ולא אמר הללויה עד שראה
במפלתן של רשעים. v'lo amar hallelujah ad she-ra'ah b'mappaltan shel resha'im. The
word הללויה hallelujah which appears very often in תהילים tehillim does not
happen until the end of 103 פרשיות, parshiyos, after it mentions the
downfall of the wicked. שנאמר יתמו חטאים מן הארץ ורשעים עוד אינם,
she-ne'emar yitamu chata'im min ha-aretz u-resha'im od einam, let the wicked end
from the world and there will no longer be any evildoers, ברכי
נפשי את ה' הללויה. barchi nafshi es hashem hallelujah. So anyway, if
you look at the side you see that's in תהילים ק"ד, tehillim
kuf daled, 104, not 103. So the גמרא Gemara says תני ק"ג.
tani kuf gimmel. What do you mean after 103? ק"ד הויין. kuf
daled havyan. It was after 104. אלא שמע מינה אשרי האיש ולמה
רגשו גוים, ela shma mina ashrei ha-ish u-lama ragshu goyim, פרק א'
ופרק ב', perek aleph u-perek beis, the first chapter 1 and 2
of תהילים, tehillim, חדא פרשה היא chada parsha hi is one פרשה.
parsha. Okay, so that's why we can use the idea of יהיו
לרצון coming at the end of chapter 19 to say it symbolizes
what we would say at the end of our 18 ברכות brachos
because really the 19 is 18, which I assume some people have
already realized corresponds exactly parallel to the שמונה עשרה because there are
18 ברכות brachos of the שמונה עשרה are actually 19 ברכות. brachos.
So this idea of 18 19 has this very beautiful nice parallel
in the 18 19 of the first פרשיות parshiyos of תהילים. tehillim.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says, דאמר רבי שמעון בר נחמני אמר
רבי יוחנן, d'amar rabbi shimon bar nachmani amar rabbi yochanan, דף י'
עמוד א', daf yod amud aleph, כל פרשה שהיתה חביבה על דוד
פתח בה באשרי וסיים בה באשרי. kol parsha she-haysah chaviva al david
pasach bah b'ashrei v'siyem bah b'ashrei. Anything that was dear to David
he opened it with אשרי ashrei and ended it with אשרי. ashrei.
פתח באשרי דכתיב אשרי האיש, pasach b'ashrei de-chtiv ashrei ha-ish, Praise is
the man, the beginning of פרק א' perek aleph of תהילים, tehillim,
וסיים באשרי דכתיב אשרי כל חוסי בו, v'siyem b'ashrei de-chtiv ashrei kol
chosei vo, Praise are all that has faith in God. And therefore
you see that he considers the beginning of פרק א' perek aleph
and the end of פרק ב' perek beis to be one פרק
perek in תהילים tehillim because it opens with אשרי ashrei and ends
with אשרי. ashrei. And again it's true also structurally as I said,
every פרק perek in תהילים tehillim begins with a key word and
that's not true about פרק ב', perek beis, and פרק ב' perek
beis actually ends with a word that echoes the beginning of פרק
א'. perek aleph. So it's very clear that it is one פרק
perek in תהילים. tehillim. Why it ever got divided into two, we
don't know. תוספות points out that there's no other place where something
opens in אשרי ashrei and ends in אשרי. ashrei. So what does
he mean every פרשה? parsha? So he says okay, but it means
something similar where it opens with a key word and ends with
a similar key word. And anyway, but he gave the example of
אשרי. ashrei. which shows that the first two פרקים Perakim in תהלים
Tehillim are really one פרק. Perek. Now the גמרא Gemara. is going
to continue to digress, now that we mentioned this פסוק Pasuk יתמו
חטאים מן הארץ, Yisamu Chata'im Min Ha'aretz, continue to digress to the
issue of what do you call it about on this on the
אגדתא Agadeta relating to this. I do want to before we get
to that just say one sentence and we'll say more about it
about the הלכה Halacha about when you say קריאת שמע. Krias Shema.
So now we said we have a couple of different times for
the morning שמע, Shema right? We have what we said in the
משנה Mishna that night שמע Shema ended at עלות, Alos, which would
suggest that day שמע Shema would start at עלות, Alos, even forgetting
the משנה, Mishna, it was explicit in an earlier ברייתא Braisa that
עלות Alos was the end of the night שמע, Shema the beginning
of the day שמע. Shema Then we have our משנה Mishna that
says that שמע Shema is משיכיר. Misheyakir, Then we have the other
opinion which seems that שמע Shema that שמע Shema is after נץ,
Netz, that the night שמע Shema goes till נץ Netz and the
and the morning שמע Shema. starts at נץ. Netz. And then we
have the opinion of אביי which sort of says you're supposed to
do שמע Shema. right before נץ. Netz. I mean
so how do you make sense out of all of this? So
the general הלכה Halacha as פסק Pasken by the רי"ף, Rif, there
are other opinions, but the general הלכה is פסק Pasken by the
רי"ף Rif is the following, is that night שמע Shema לכתחילה L'chatchila
goes till עלות, Alos, but בדיעבד B'diavad like בשעת הדחק, B'sha'as Had'chak,
if you remember the גמרא Gemara before when it introduced the idea
that night שמע Shema goes till נץ, Netz, said you can be
סומך Somech on רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon בשעת הדחק. B'sha'as Had'chak. So
בשעת הדחק B'sha'as Had'chak you can say the night שמע Shema until
הנץ החמה Hanetz Hachama until sunrise, but you're really supposed to say
it till עלות. Alos. Day שמע Shema starts when you need to,
like you're going on a trip or whatever, it can be as
early as עלות, Alos, which is that פשט, Pshat, so the basic
פסק Psak is the עלות Alos cutoff for the night שמע Shema
the beginning of the day שמע. But it's ideal to be it's
better to start at משיכיר, Misheyakir. עלות Alos is only a בדיעבד,
B'diavad, and right and
that's the and that's the basic difference about the
terms of the
שמע. So and then the ותיקין is a separate practice to try
to ideally get the שמע right before sunrise and the שמונה עשרה
right after sunrise. So that's like a way the רי"ף Rif tries
to sort of organize that material in terms of like what's לכתחילה,
L'chatchila, what's בדיעבד, B'diavad, and to some degree like פסק Pasken like
all of them. And then there becomes questions about can you even
do it in contradictory ways? Can you say like both the night
שמע and the day שמע between עלות Alos and הנץ החמה, Hanetz
Hachama, which it seems very clearly that you cannot. But that the
basic פסק Psak is that עלות Alos is the cutoff time.
בדיעבד B'diavad you can sometimes do night שמע after עלות Alos and
certainly and שמע ideally of the day should not be before משיכיר.
That at least is the פסק Psak of the רי"ף Rif and
the general sort of פסק Psak that we tend to adopt. Okay,
so we'll so there's more to say about that and the בעל
המאור Ba'al Hamaor has a fascinating read about all of this, but
we'll leave it at that for now. So now let's just continue
a little bit more in the
גמרא. Gemara
הני בריוני, Hani Biryonei, certain types of boors or
troublemakers
דהוו בשיבבותיה דרבי מאיר Dehavu B'shivavusei D'Rabbi Meir were in the neighborhood
of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. A very famous גמרא Gemara here. דהוו
קא מצערו ליה טובא Dehavu Ka Matza'aru Lei Tuva where they were
causing him a lot of anguish. הוה קא בעי רבי מאיר רחמי
עלוייהו כי היכי דלימותו, Hava Ka Ba'ei Rabbi Meir Rachmei Alaihu Ki
Heichi Dilimusu, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was praying for them they should
die. This might remind you about the earlier גמרא Gemara that tried
the rabbi who tried to get the exact moment that God got
angry in order to cause
the מין, Min, the heretic or whatever to die. Anyway, here רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir was just doing a straight prayer to God that
they should die. אמרה ליה ברוריא דביתהו, Amra Lei Beruriah Devis'hu, so
ברוריא Beruriah his wife said to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, מאי דעתך,
Mai Da'atach, what what are you thinking? משום דכתיב Mishum Dechsiv the
פסוק Pasuk says יתמו חטאים מן הארץ, Yisamu Chata'im Min Ha'aretz, let
the wicked be ceased from from the world. מי כתיב חוטאים? Mi
Ksiv Chot'im? It doesn't say the sinners. חטאים כתיב. Chata'im Ksiv. The
חטאים Chata'im with okay, the real פשט Pshat of the פסוק Pasuk
is sinners, but nevertheless here's how she's choosing to read it. That
it means not sinners but sins. ועוד שפיל לסיפיה דקרא, Ve'od Shpil
L'seifei Dekra, look at the end of the פסוק, Pasuk, ורשעים עוד
אינם, Ursha'im Od Einam, that the wicked are no longer, meaning it's
like a natural consequence. The wicked just disappear, they're not destroyed. So
how does that happen that the wicked just naturally disappear? So she
said, כיון דייתמו חטאים, Keivan Deyisamu Chata'im,
if the sins cease, ורשעים עוד אינם, Ursha'im Od Einam, then
the wicked will just disappear, will go away, if there's no sinning
there's no wicked. אלא בעי רחמי עלוייהו דלהדרו בתשובה, Ela Ba'ei Rachmei
Alaihu Dilehadru B'shuvah, you should pray
for them to do תשובה, Tshuvah, ורשעים עוד אינם, Ursha'im Od Einam,
and then there will be no longer wicked wicked people in this
world. בעי רחמי עלוייהו, Ba'ei Rachmei Alaihu, so he prayed for them,
והדרו בתשובה, Vahadru B'shuvah, and they did תשובה. Tshuvah. So this is
a very famous story about ברוריא Beruriah besting רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and not just besting him but also very much if you would
a more... מידת הרחמים middat harachamim here than a מידת הדין middat
hadin and trying not just to get back at them but to
do something that is not just good for you but good for
them and good for the world. So אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי amar
leh hahu tzadoki now we're not done. A certain... What?
Rabbi,
what do you mean by the words בעי רחמי? bei rachmei? Okay?
He asked for רחמים rachamim that they should die. What do you
make of that? This is a very strange formulation. Maybe you just
prayed but בעי רחמי... bei rachmei... Yeah, that's a good point.
רחמי rachamei is a word that's used in the גמרא Gemara for
תפילה. Maybe it means... I mean I assume here if we were
to translate it literally it would mean רחמים rachamim for himself. But
you're saying בעי רחמי עילוייהו bei rachmei ilvayeihu on them. Yeah, I
think
you're right. It's a fascinating point. Maybe...
I just interpreted this not, you know, the word רחמים rachamei is
a standard word for תפילה. So I just translated it as he
prayed for them that they should die. But you're right in the
sense of the literal meaning, compassion for them. You know, maybe it's
better that they should die and not continue to sin. You know,
it's not just good for him, it's good for them too. And
ברוריה Brurya says if you really care about them it's not that
they would just die and stop sinning, it's that they would do
תשובה. teshuva. So that's a possibility, I hadn't stopped to think about
that. Okay, so now another story. A certain גרסא girsa says צדוקי,
tzadoki, but the original גרסא girsa is מין. min. And one of
the reasons that the גרסא girsa have been edited, I don't know
what your גמרא Gemara shows, but there's been a little censoring is
that מינים minim in the
גמרא very often refer to Hebrew Christians, to Jewish Christians at the
time of, you know, when they were not yet clearly a distinct
religion yet, but they were believers of Jesus and מין min often
refers to that and therefore in the period of self-censorship when the
church was starting to pay attention to what was written in the
גמרא because the apostates were telling them, there was a change of
מין min to צדוקי. tzadoki. But anyway the original text is מין
min here. Anyway a certain heretic or מין... min...
some text is set back...
Yeah I think I yeah I think I think Artscroll's pretty good
about actually restoring some of the original text, which is a very
nice to see. Okay, so a certain מין min said to ברוריה,
Brurya, כתיב. ktiv. So here he is having a direct discussion with
ברוריה. Brurya. Maybe... so he says it's written 'רני עקרה לא ילדה',
roni akara lo yalada, rejoice oh barren one who has not given
birth. So he says, what does that mean? 'משום דלא ילדה רני',
mishum d'lo yalada roni, because you haven't given birth you should rejoice?
And obviously the point is that in the end you're, you know,
you'll have children once again, but anyway hyper-focusing on that פסוק. pasuk.
So
אמר ליה, amar leh, so she said to him... one wonders if
perhaps there's a little bit of a, again if this is in
the Christian context, if this is maybe a little trying to make
some proof about virgin birth or something about somebody who can't give
birth who did give birth, I don't know. Anyway, so what did
she say back to him? So אמר ליה, amar leh, she said
back to him: 'שטיא', shatya, idiot! 'שפיל לסיפא דקרא', shpil l'seifa d'kra,
look at the end of the פסוק, pasuk, which was the same
phrase used before. Look at the end of the פסוק. pasuk. 'דכתיב
כי רבים בני שוממה מבני בעולה אמר ה'', d'ktiv ki rabbim bnei
shomema m'bnei be'ula amar Hashem, because
greater are those are the children of the desolate one, meaning of
Jerusalem, from those that have been, you know, בעולה be'ula that have
had sex, meaning of the prosperous one, of אדום Edom and so
on. So the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is in the
end the children of Jerusalem will be greater than the children of,
you know, of the destroying country. But how does she read it?
אלא מאי עקרה לא ילדה? ela mai akara lo yalada? So what
does it mean the עקרה akara that has not given birth? 'רני
כנסת ישראל שדומה לאשה עקרה שלא ילדה בנים לגיהנם כוותייכו'. roni knesset
yisrael shedome l'isha akara shelo yalda banim l'gehinnom k'vatyichu. So praised is
the congregation of Israel that she has not given birth to children
that are going to גיהנם gehinnom like you. So she's happy that
she is barren from children that are going straight to גיהנם gehinnom
as opposed to you who's going straight to גיהנם. gehinnom. So interesting
response. Okay, so אמר ליה ההוא צדוקי לרבי אבהו. amar leh hahu
tzadoki l'Rabbi Abbahu. Now that we're talking about מינים minim and sort
of debates with Rabbis we'll read one more and we'll end with
it. So צדוקי tzadoki said to Rabbi Abbahu, כתיב 'מזמור לדוד בבורחו
מפני אבשלום בנו'. ktiv mizmor l'David b'vorcho mipnei Avshalom b'no. A song
to David when he ran away from Absalom his son. So it
says, וכתוב 'לדוד מכתם בבורחו מפני שאול במערה'. v'chtiv l'David michtam b'vorcho
mipnei Shaul b'me'ara. To David is a מכתם michtam when he ran
away from Saul and he was hiding in the cave. 'היי מיסא
הוה ברישא'? hei maisa hava b'reisha? Which one happened first? 'מכדי מעשה
שאול הוה ברישא', michdi ma'aseh Shaul hava b'reisha, the story of Saul
happened first, before Absalom, right, before he was even king. 'נכתוב ברישא',
nichtov b'reisha, why not why isn't that written first? Why is the
Absalom one written, you know, in תהלים ג', Tehillim gimmel, and this
one only in תהלים נ"ז? Tehillim nun zayin? אמר ליה, so he
said to him, 'אתון דלא דרשיתון סמוכים קשיא לכו'. atun d'lo darshitu
smuchim kashya l'chu. You that don't make דרשות drashot about juxtaposed פסוקים,
psukim, so you're bothered with this. 'אנן דדרשינן סמוכים לא קשיא לן',
anan d'darshinan smuchim lo kashya lan, we make these types of דרשות,
drashot, this is not a problem for us. דאמר רבי יוחנן 'סמוכין
מן התורה מנין'? d'amar Rabbi Yochanan smuchin min haTorah minayin? Where do
you know the idea of juxtaposed פסוקים psukim is significant in the
Torah? שנאמר 'סמוכים לעעד לעולם עשוים באמת וישר'. shene'emar smuchim la'ad l'olam
asuyim b'emet v'yashar. So which clearly means supports forever and ever are
made in truth and righteousness. Anyway, so he understands... understanding that the
תורה, Torah, the סמוכין, smuchin, the way things are juxtaposed, there's truth
to them, there's a meaning in the way they're juxtaposed. So what's,
how's that an answer? למה נסמכה פרשת אבשלום לפרשת גוג ומגוג? Lama
nismacha parshas Avshalom leparshas Gog u-Magog? So why is this פרשה parsha
of אבשלום Avshalom juxtaposed? Because this is going back to the earlier
discussion of the first two פרקים perakim of תהילים. Tehillim. So the
first two פרקים perakim of תהילים, Tehillim, the end of פרק ב
Perek Beis alluded to the world, the גוג ומגוג, Gog u-Magog, right,
Armageddon and the time of משיח, Mashiach and then it's אבשלום. Avshalom.
So why are they juxtaposed? שיאמר לך אדם, Sheyomar lach adam, כלום
יש עבד שמורד ברבו, klum yesh eved shemored berabo, if anybody were
to say, oh, how could the story of גוג ומגוג Gog u-Magog
ever come true? That's a story about a slave rebelling against his
master. אבל תאמר לו, Aval temer lo, you say back to him,
so כלום יש בן שמורד באביו? klum yesh ben shemored beaviv? Have
you ever heard about a son rebelling against his father? אלא הוה
הכא, Ella hava hacha, it was that way, אלא הוה, ella hava,
הכא נמי הוה, hacha nami hava, here too it was that way,
and there too the מלחמת גוג ומגוג Milchemes Gog u-Magog will come
the same way אבשלום Avshalom rebelled against דוד. Now, I'll just end
by saying if you assume a Christian context to this, it obviously
takes on a different significance. Because number one is, you know, the
idea about the sort of coming of משיח Mashiach, and the Messianic
coming and that it's sort of, you know, that doubting sort of,
if you would, the מלחמת גוג ומגוג Milchemes Gog u-Magog which is
where we put the coming of the משיח, Mashiach you know, them
putting the coming of the משיח elsewhere. And then the, and then
the proof that it's possible is that a son rebels against the
father. So one wonders if there's a little bit of a subtext
here about the son who you, you know, your idea of the
son rebelling against the תורה Torah
and what really is the, you know, and rebelling against the father
as it were. Again, that's my read, I don't know, but it
certainly I think is, is suggestive here if you assume that it's
a debate with a Hebrew Christian and not just with some random
person. Okay, we will end with that, to pick, to be picked
up tomorrow and then we'll start doing a, you know, a double
session each day until we catch up. Okay, see you all in
person tomorrow.
Bye.